um yeah I just wanted I just want to
make myself available that's all yeah
thank you I appreciate that a lot
I um you know one of the whole thing
about our relationship to the potential
yeah how we can fall in love with it and
and it's ended relationship to the
actual but the two differences between
those you know I've often wondered about
when we see somebody right when I see
you and I perceive you right it's such a
strange thing to know exactly what I'm
perceiving if I can you know I didn't
exercise that that that I sometimes do
with and in my courses well I'll have
somebody kind of make eye contact with
each other and then have one person like
look look at the other's eye and then
describe the intimate like physical
details of it until they get into that
perceptual switch where they they're not
looking at a person they're looking at
an eyeball and then having your eye
there and say okay now see them and
there's this kind of experience and in
it and it seems to make experiencial
this this mystery that yeah what was I
looking at what was the difference right
like am i when I see you and my is it an
actual am I seeing physical objects well
not quite because it's like when i zoom
into the object it's not like I see you
it's not the same experience but when I
when I I let go of the object miss and I
see you there's a different apprehension
oh very much yeah I'm wondering if that
apprehension is what we is a way of
talking about that we perceive one's
potential that's interesting let me
reflect on that for a moment I mean
there's one sense in which I mean even
speaking psychologically like organisms
don't respond mostly to the physical
properties they respond to the meaning
that's why the sight of the flame the
smell of the
smoke the noise of someone saying fire
or run can all cause the same behavior
because they share meaning even though
they're very physically different and
part of what you might be suggesting and
I think the meaning is often carried you
get more and more meaning as you move up
to higher levels of organization so when
you move to the I to the face the face
is often more meaningful the eye and
then the person is more meaningful or
their or their full body and then the
moving body is more meaningful than the
still body etc etc and so there's
there's definitely what what that means
is both there's an increased actual
actualization of some sort of structural
functional organization but that that I
mean if we follow up on Aristotle was
way and we're using his term so he
better invoke him at least once like
that actuality is the capacity to act
and so I mean when we're encountering
that more meaning we're encountering
right that the person is and if are in
if action is more meaning based than
just physical feature based then when
we're encountering more meaning I'm
trying to do this right on the fly here
guy as we encounter more meaning we're
actually encountering a greater capacity
to act that's what I that's what I'm
trying to suggest so that's interesting
because I hadn't thought about quite
doing that before with Aristotle that
idea of you know that there's this
there's this coordination between being
more meaningful being more actual and
being more capable of more more
meaningful behavior yeah yeah that did
that track at all did that work thank
you but basically I heard you say is the
more but the more the more potential I
can see the more I can act into which
which gives me the ability to both well
it's like it's like the potential and
the actual like is does the word realize
yes that's why I use that words a lot
yeah
is something I'm wondering about like
this is what he's talking about that
it's like oh that relationship between
the actual the potential and that when
we act into it in such a way that the
more of the potential is realized but
also more of the ground this is closed
yes right so it's like it's like there's
a deef relationship between being
informed in Aristotle sense being
actualized to greater levels of
structural function organization and the
capacity to generate information in in
terms of patterns of intelligibility in
the world there seems to be a direct
relationship there that I think is
something that I can now I hadn't put
this together but I see that that's
something that Platonists was was was
sort of you know drawing out of and
developing out of Aristotle yeah because
you know because Platonists takes the
the levels and Aristotle's conformity
theory and then he turns it into like
any me and he connects it with the
Platonic Anna got the idea that when I
can fit myself to a particular level of
of intelligibility then that will
actualize me to a certain degree but it
will also disclose reality as more
meaningful to me in a coordinated
fashion yeah that seems right so to
ground it back down in the exercise the
the attentional scaling you're doing
when you're getting people to move
between feature and Gestalt yeah and
then notice the change and especially
there if you're doing it in a certain
context I can see why this is so
important yeah is because right you're
you're not what you're doing is you're
doing that you're you're getting people
to suddenly experience that sort of
expanse of birth of meaning in the
object but it's also causing them to
change to a different level of
processing power if I can put it that
way right that but that totally and I
think particularly well at least what
I'm attempting to do in that exercise is
to take something that just seems so
given an ordinary and reveal the end
meanness of it Oh totally and I think
that's any you're triggering the insight
machinery when you're when you're
playing between I mean I think that's
what drives a lot of insight is the you
know when you zoom in you scale down you
break
normal frames yeah and then when you
zoom back out you're making new frames
that you didn't have before and so and
you're very much especially again like
an if that's done within a circling
context in which people are in a
participatory mode that's gonna engender
wonder because the very process of
framing is also going to come in to
their awareness and they're gonna start
to wonder about what is going on in all
this sort of sense making yes oh yeah Oh
totally and that's it yes I just want to
say one thing just so you know sorry I'm
just bubbling with excitement here this
is this is the kind of thing I want to
do more of I mean right we're you know
within with India logos where we try to
articulate where we try to bring some
theoretical articulation to what's going
on in the process so that we can if
possible you know make connections to
the cognitive science in a way that will
be mutually informing between the
practice and the science and part of
what I would like to to be doing I know
what I you understand I don't want to
just sit back and theorize that's um
what I'm talking about if I talk about
what we're doing here yeah oh yeah in
fact I just I so I've read you know I've
read more books because of you and the
last and I've looked but I just got yeah
giving me the beepers with like insights
the one I just I just I'm on I think the
last chapter of is this one this is
after thinking and being is um yes it's
called philosophy the it's about the
prac it's about the practical i'ts that
but actually we're philosophy comes from
is is not is is a set of practices right
Christopher says you read a really you
read it a lot before before you teach
sometimes
is it is it Hado or let me just look
here one second it's um it's this
philosophy is a way of life yeah I do
its philosophy is a way of life by ID oh
yes very much that's what I thought it
was yes very much
yeah I think I think reading Perl and
hodo close together he's an excellent
thing to do because pearl pearls stuff
is so clear I mean he says I was the one
that wrote thinking being thinking being
right in his and in you know he starts
that chapter and he's trying to talk
about how you know the philosophical
project of trying to understand being
and I knew this would resonate with you
is in is in one important sense you know
a religious project because it requires
significant transformation on the part
of the individual confronting it and
then when you read that and pearls doing
all that and it's completely legitimate
argument and he's tracing out this cold
tonic heritage late Pearl's book on
Dionysius on a theophany
is the best book on pseudo-dionysius
I've ever read all right and hands down
but then but the thing with pearl is if
you haven't read the hadou you're sort
of left with you but how do I do this
like what does that mean right and then
hodo talks about no no no you know you
have to understand that ancient
philosophy is much more about the
transformative process no Spiritual
Exercises in a way of life than it is
about the discourse the discourse is
always in the service right of the
aspirational transformation and I think
if you put therefore if you put hadou
and pearl together you get you get a you
get a real well I'll use your language
you really get the world
yeah of ancient philosophy you really do
you really get the world of ancient
philosophy I think quite well in a way
in which you know and again I can speak
for this directly because I was taught
this then until recently the way in
which academic philosophy didn't really
represent ancient philosophy well
it was like you know there's been a
change and there's people like a doe and
there's people like you're send at tea
and other people but for a very long
time it was just the extraction of the
propositions and the examination of the
arguments and mm-hmm you know you're not
you you weren't getting you were getting
that world in any way as if you could
kind of like no philosophy and
understand philosophy without being
changed by it
well very much and I think and I think I
think this is a mistake I remember my
IRA and co-authored former student of
mine he took some of my ideas and he
said you know the thing about modern
theology that what shape what makes
modern theology modern right and you see
it with happening with with people like
round with ah kameez you don't have to
go through transformation to get to
ultimate reality you just manipulate the
propositions and then philosophy picks
up on that idea right that it can do
metaphysics it can talk about what's
ultimate without requiring any
significant transformation this is
triggered I just had I'm just talking to
Jordan Hall man we're just spinning off
of each other and this really wonderful
we've a and we're talking it we were
talking about because I was asking him
this question and and we were and I sort
of said I want to I want to dialogue
about it but we were talking about there
you know when you're trying to get into
relationship with transcendence right
there I was suggesting to him that it's
it's it's like you to use something like
with the four kinds of knowing like not
triangulation but Quadra angulations or
something where all four of them are
sort of converging towards the horizon
to use your term right yeah and and that
so so the proposition was in there but
right but there's this there's this
there's this vertical integration within
the person the Sun so platonic right
that actually affords you because the
idea is here's the here's the idea I'm
playing with right now it's serious play
one right is the complexification of the
of the knowings the way that they are
each still differentiated from each
other each finding what is particularly
relevant to them but there's also a
relevance realization occurring between
them that
complexification of the whole person
gives you like the best machinery for
coupling to you know the complexity of
the world in a sense that you can better
sense the ultimate bomb through it not
yeah and I wish and I was thinking about
your you know circling and other than
these other practices and and Jordan was
saying oh yeah yeah I get that that
there's that there's that sense of that
um right so I just want to express that
to you because it's sort of uppermost in
my mind and it sort of being like it's
just sort of sort of bubbling through me
that this that you know that that sense
that and I get that that's what was
going on in ancient philosophical
practice even when it was doing things
like ontology right even when it was
doing ontology it was like we got it we
got it first all we have to engage and
activate and complexify the whole person
set it into a transformative relation
and only in that will you adduce right
yet the inexhaustibility of reality yes
now I'm just curious right now the way
that this is coming together to you
hearing is this are we inside of some
like that kind of very process like if
it feels like it it feels like it
appears so I typically when I'm moving
around a lot I'm playing with the
perspective my my hands are doing lots
of respect double star I'm trying to
trigger all kinds of procedural stuff
and then I mean you know and then I'm
trying to put this into an existential
relevance I'm trying to engage like you
the the the machinery of the self and
the thing that's calling that all
together the horizon that's like calling
that deeper complex that that deeper
complexification of yourselves
that's the this is what I really got in
this in both of these books that I that
I rare this this this sense in which the
in in ancient philosophy there was this
sense in which the the propositional
knowing was to exemplify what the way of
the way when lived words they're words
that you could say it was you know how
they say where
method always precedes theory right
first he does something right and then
it but they don't really know how they
how they do it they just do it and then
people see it they're like then they
they start to make theories about it
right yep and then ideally the theories
that we make support a deepening yes
what was embodied in that I guess that's
like going from from like dear Ora
to theory to thei aura that thing yes
yeah so this is this is the thing that
sort of reverberating in me right now
there's sort of multidimensionality of
dialectic as I put it so there's a
wonderful mouthful that you won't put on
a bumper sticker right so we've all
we've obviously got this going on right
between you and I and then you and I
have talked already about and this
already gets us into the transformative
relationship with the ontology right
you've got this going on between you
know the dialectic between levels
ontological levels but now there's the
third dimension which you've just
mentioned there's the constant dialectic
between the kinds of knowing exemplified
in the dialectic between theory and
theory and they're constantly talking to
each other as well and all three of
these are like really exemplified in
Socratic dialectic it's all there
happening in this really fluent
integrated fashion this is what I'm
really excited about trying to convey to
people because I also see this right I
also see I think you know you know going
to the circling practice now I see this
happening in the circling and I and I
also see people even marking it like
phenomenologically and and
propositioning though like they'll do
okay I'll try it I'm not trying to
imitate in marketing video no no no this
is done respectfully but they'll be
they'll be they'll be in right to sort
of centring centered in the room right
between everybody and then they'll build
off and they'll fall back right and then
you can see that they're there they're
trying to do some theory they're trying
to ok what's going like they're trying
to get some intelligible structure to
this because they want to be able to
bring it because if they can't do that
they can't bring it back
words and then they did it and then you
can sometimes they get stuck there for a
while and you can see them sort of and
they it's funny how much they make their
day they hold themselves back to almost
gesturally convey that they're sort of
stuck in theory and then what will
happen it and people will often notice
they'll say oh I thought you just moved
back into your chest
yeah right and then you see them sort of
I don't know functions out what it is
but it's said they go from here and then
the urna right and they come in and you
can oh no okay now they're back into now
they're back into furia again so this is
going on and then of course people are
the dialogue moves between different
ontological levels seamlessly and then
of course people connect and then
reconnect and connect and reconnect and
then and and and and then there's a kind
of hyper coherence that gels um I just
sorry I mean I'm just getting into this
but I'm I'm trying to like I said I'm
trying to do a thority I'm trying to
talk in a way that facilitates the
participation but also allows the
connection to cognitive science yes
totally and I and I I'm so appreciating
everything that you're saying because
all that's real super familiar and those
those movements back and forth through
when people go oh oh those are like you
capture those things you can almost you
can almost say I I sometimes joke and
I'm like you know basically all you need
to do is walk into a room someone says
something and someone goes ah and there
you go can you say that another way yeah
they're present is something opened up
they got something yet it's not yet
theory yes that's right
something was unconcealed and then say
it another way and then they struggle in
the articulation of it and then somebody
else goes hmm and you're like keep doing
that long enough eventually you'll hit
God you know yeah
well it's funny because that's what
Jordan and I were getting to we were
talking about there cuz I was talking
about because he had I don't know if you
saw it yet I highly recommend it
Jordan and Jonathan page oh yeah yeah
I actually texted you the link to it
here they are you seen it yeah oh I just
went a side I want it I want to share
something because I shared this with
Jordan because I was deeply appreciative
so there was a moment when he said you
know I'm gonna call him Johnny V and and
and there was you know it was quite a
bit of an infection as I was lady to him
not that long ago somebody who is a
friend not a close friend what you'd
call a social friend but nevertheless
within that context somebody I I really
liked and I I tutored her daughter well
she died recently and the thing was you
know she was the other person that
called me and she just stood up
spontaneously she called me Johnny V and
she used to do it all the time
oh and so when he did that a person for
whom I'm having growing affection and
connection and then it connected me to
that other person see when I was like
when I was living there I was very
displaced because I was in a very
suburban environment and there were its
but I and I was often reminded of how
much I did not belong there I put that
aside for now but she was a beacon she
she very much reached out and she did
this you know repeatedly with affection
and humor and it was often in the kind
of social social situations that I would
find very challenging she she was very
much a beacon in that way and so for
Jordan to call that out and cuz that was
just I just it was really really a
powerful moment for me and I just I just
thank him I said they're just you know
there's I just wanted to say thank you
for doing that so that's a that's the
that's the aside but we were talking
about this and this gives me brings me
back to parole you know the stuff we're
talking about in this
multidimensionality right dialectic and
I would say cuz you know what comes
across and pearl is if you're in this
dialectic transformative coupling it's
you experience it as sacred you can't
experience it as anything else it just
is yeah right and what's astonishing is
I mean I don't I don't want to be
dismissive
but how can people like what would it
me to do theology in which you're doing
theology doesn't make you yeah come or
do to ontology then and you're not
coming in to write like your your
there's no there's no sacredness there's
no yeah wonder and law you know you got
a professional life no no that's not
fair Plato and Platina saying they run
schools for decades and yet this is
clearly present throughout their entire
career yeah yeah and so it just struck
me as something that has you know that's
been fundamentally lost in in some way
and and so we were talking about that we
were talking about you in Jordan yeah
you enjoy it Jordan and I because well
you're part of this discourse where you
know we're wrestling with this issue of
you know the religion that's not a
religion what does that mean and like
anyway and again what does it mean not
just in theory but what does it mean in
theory what does it mean in dialectic
what does it mean in theory what does it
mean and dialectic of course we have to
do the theory because there's existing
theories where you have a responsibility
to them yeah but right but but but but
beyond that what does it mean in Fiore
a-- what does it mean in dialectic like
what does it mean for news what does it
mean for ya all of that yeah totally
what do one other thing I'm getting is
that well somewhere along the line what
got split apart and this is one of
things I want to talk with you about is
sure is first of all kind of getting
like how Socrates is custom underlying
everything right for me historically
just this said that you know the dissent
the sense in which the sense in which
the the love of wisdom philosophy
philosophy ax Wright was a was about a
profound relationship with that which is
most near yourself and that which is
most cosmological at once right oh my
gosh I'm so glad you said that because
I've been thinking about you and your
nearness farness when I've been reading
some of this stuff about Socrates and
you know how much self-knowledge just
did you know
well is it yourself the thing that's
most familiar to you well in one sense
yes but it's also the thing that's most
mysterious and if I don't if I don't
properly inhabit it then I'm I can't get
to the depths of really yeah the
nearness farness in self-knowledge and
Socratic self-knowledge like I can hear
you in my head when I'm when I'm reading
that stuff when I'm reading it in
Moore's book or I'm reading it
especially in Roth Facebook or in
Socratic knowledge in platonic or
Socratic ignorance in platonic knowledge
yeah they're very much and and and and
that that that and that therefore
there's there here this is bold but
there is there there is no way to drink
those non-logical identities together
what's near was far other than through
radical aspirational transformation yeah
there is no way to realize that self
except through radical aspirational
transformation because that's the only
way in which those can be brought into
relationship to each other yes in that
in that in that it seems like the the
ancients seem to just know right
and they even knew that they knew this
is that the propositional was one is to
is to is to is is to come to terms with
what they were actually experiencing
first right so that that they can go
back and go further in right you go back
down into the cave right two
propositions was was that wasn't the
point that was the thing that held is
kind of like that was it helped create
structure right in what's really
interesting is to hear I couldn't I'm
still comprehensiveness comprehending
this that it like given especially in
the you know the way that I think they
call it half is the Hellenism where when
when Alexander the Great
basically kind of world and there were
all these it's there how long that
period considered for about
so it's considered it's so most people
you know sort of 300 BCE till around you
know when it changes into the Roman
Empire you know it's the Hellenistic
period is sort of over when Rome is
coming into sort of full ascendance
because then the legacy right of our the
Chris Chris and Philip and I wrote about
this in the book and we wrote about how
the Hellenistic period is a period of
pervasive dama sight and so you've got
something very analogous to our current
meeting crisis going on there me and
that's when the therapeutic aspect of
philosophy gets really strongly
developed and integrated in well what
was fascinating to me is just to think
about that there have been lines of
thought like um you know
Epicurus race duis ism the cynics
Platonists that battle schools that have
worked for thousand you know for that
whole period of time like survived all
this change that no know about and you
think about it well given how spread out
everything was and given obviously there
was a printing presses most people to do
it like it's mostly cool culture that
you could have all of that dominant side
all of that intermingling and then
there's this these deep these deep deep
basically philosophical ideas that were
passed on and yeah Nathan right over
time that is first of all that's that is
profoundly stable right there's a
stability there and and but what's
interesting is that it gave that
stability yet the theory right was in
service right right to the fiora right
active that right yeah much yeah and and
I think it seems so important and I
think this is what I'm starting to
appreciate what you are doing right what
you're trying to highlight from within
the academic set
which is impressive right because it
seems like the academic set setting is
it like if the theory's your experience
doesn't really matter right for its it's
the thing for human resources or it's
the thing to go to therapy about but
like the thing that matters is your
propositions and and all that but I just
think I think it's just telling about
like that the theory does hold right it
can hold but when it's in right
relationship to the transformation of
the person yes
and Socrates exemplifies that
integration yeah completely
and he's so I mean hadou talks about is
there's an essay in that book the figure
of Socrates right the figure of Socrates
is as important as anything Socrates
ever said because he precise he is so
identified with that project at least in
the Platonic version of Socrates he's so
identified with that that product of
exemplifying always exemplifying never
just speaking and in fact many of the
many of the dialogues indicate that the
speaking sort of bankrupts because
what's actually carrying the dialogue
forward is the transformation that is
being exemplified in Socrates right and
what is it mate so this is one of the
thing this kind of gets us into our I
think our condition now right like this
like I think Heidegger has a bead on
this that is horrifying notion of like
the mania of technique right of like
what what I think the Nietzsche in this
way that probably drove him insane right
was able to like name the Anto theology
of the time while in with time right
which is we go from we go from this
sense this implicit explicit sense that
that that the cosmic and the most like
the far and the near are one writers in
this very sophisticated way right and it
like seemed took it seemed to underlie
the way people lived in the way in in
different levels
it affords aspiration because though you
have to have those there has to be
connection between them Oh or my current
self for my future self are not
connected yeah totally to where now the
only thing that seen is valid and even
with post-modernism is becoming that's
that that's being being underpinned
right which is basically the sense in
which where reality is somehow in the
proposition and that and that your
experience right is if it's connected to
that at all it's not it's seen as
subordinate to that to the propositional
no way and I was I was thinking about
this this is one of the big things that
I just I texted it to you I see if I can
find it so I can kind of quote it it was
who is in thinking being where he was
talking about Pluto nice and the sense
of being as intelligibility yeah that's
right oh so central
that's that I think pearls right that's
the thing that runs from Plato through
to clitoris yes even into Aquinas in
some ways yes and it's and it seems like
that I think that far as I can tell
Heidegger really inherited that sense of
like it goes the being of being is the
inexhaustible horizon of intelligibility
I think so I mean I I think that's part
of what's going on I think you can see
Heidegger wrestling with something that
okay so part of what I think I think
this is a good a good response to what
we're doing here little see him off
kilter a for a sec but part of what the
meaning crisis is is we've lost we've
lost Socrates to put it into a slogan
we've lost that that and there's that
there's a phrase in Nietzsche that's
really really important to me and I
gotta talk about it in the series he
says because he's very critical of
Socrates throughout all of his writings
but he but he there's this moment of
disclosure he says I hate Socrates
I reject Socrates or Socrates as false
notice notice right
I hate Socrates he is so close to me I'm
always fighting him because you see
what's going on with Nietzsche right
he's he he's proposing right he's
proposing the ubermensch but he's not
actually providing right anything other
than discourse and he's struggling and
you can see him struggling with trying
to but and he can't turn to the Platonic
tradition because he rejects the the
metaphysical position he thinks it
represents the two worlds mythology and
so he like he keeps getting drawn to
somebody right and then I think this is
what I think this is why he had this
profound ambivalence toward Socrates
because the project of the ubermensch is
right is a project that requires you
have to do something like what Socrates
did you have to bring in all the
transformation you have to bring in
right the the right the the the
participatory knowing that coupling to
the inexhaustible right and and and
indeed she knew she's in she's in a box
he can't get out of that and I think
hiding it because while I talked about
this before but good because Nietzsche
is basically just negating you know
Christian the Christian until Anto
theology of his time and and I see
Heidegger struggling to get out of that
and and see so I mean how digger it with
the neologisms and the way he writes
he's trying to engage yeah these other
aspects um I have some criticisms of
Heidegger at that point but but I do see
him that he he sees I mean this is how
I'm reading him he sees that there's
that there's he's got to do something
fundamentally different what need she
did and that that that that that right
the the that something like an agog a
that the there is no ubermensch with out
right anna gaga
yeah least that's how i'm reading part
and so part of anna got good real quick
an agave again okay so an agave is the
is this I think one of their sort of
profound insights in in Plato that I
think it gets very clearly articulated
annex located in finest and the idea is
one of the things that drives my
self-deception is I have conflict within
my psyche my psyche is in that sense
disordered and lacking in
intelligibility and then one of the
things that wisdom does is it more
properly aligned and we've been talking
about these alignment ideas all through
our dialogue write it more properly
aligns and thereby reduces right that
interest because the interest psychic
conflict if my appetites are not
properly in dialogue with my reason
I'll myself because things will
be improperly super salient to me etc so
if I get those if I get what political
the inner justice right I'm gonna reduce
the the self-deception but as I reduce
the self-deception and we will fight
about this earlier it's gonna open up my
capacity my insight to see deeper deeper
patterns of reality but then as I get as
I taste deeper reality as I develop a
taste for mental reality
I then internalize that back and I can
more fully get at the depths of the the
machinery of the psyche and then the
whole thing does this its cycles because
they mutually afford each other and what
I get is I get two of my strongest meta
drives being Co satisfied my desire for
inner peace and my desire to be in
contact with what what is most real and
that's that's this is the anagen
transformation ya know what latina is
added to that because it's implicit I
think in Plato's allegory of the cave is
but what this means is it's I'm not just
cycling this way you see it and and agog
a means to ascend because as they said
you know as as my psyche let's say let's
say it more properly aligned go back to
our earlier thing the four kinds of
knowing and they complexify and that
that allows me it enables me to confront
more of the dynamical complexity of
reality so reality can now be more
disclosed to me I can couple to it right
and then that's gonna tutor me I'm gonna
be able to internalize that in right and
so I the my complexification and the
complexity of reality
are coupled together in mutual like in
this in this pattern of conformity
conforming right I das intelligibility
patterns and so I think what Heidegger
is trying to do with Alafaya I wish he'd
said it I think he was struggling but I
think part of what he's trying to do
with Alafaya is get us to that sense of
the an agogic disclosure of truth as
opposed to just a mere presentation all
right all right so you know in Alafaya
right the things are disclosed but
they're disclosed there disclosed in a
resonant fashion right not just
disclosed right and and and and and
that's why he talks so much about your
comportment you know and he invokes he
invokes Annie Oakley in the Oakland onic
idea the leis in height right but yeah I
have some criticisms of Glazer night
because I think it's it's it's too far I
think he's overreacting to the Cartesian
imposition of the will and he's going so
I agree with Barfield that he shouldn't
have gone through the leis in height
because that's only half of that cart
yeah he's and I has to be paired with
Dirk Brook breakthrough Dirk Brook
breakthrough has to go laser night and
Dirk Brook have to always be held
together yeah I mean you're trying to
write and he's about breakthrough and
what we're talking about with the
circling breakthrough at the break a be
an appropriate frame and then I have to
move through to a bigger friend right
right
well it's also interesting you think
about circling like that the practice of
circling he is simply practice is being
with what is yes well you get you know
that sounds can sound really static but
that's not when you get into it know is
is unfolds and what's interesting is is
by you know this is kind of a co an
right that you chew on with with
circling is is let go of your agendas
we're not trying to get anywhere but
what's interesting it doesn't mean that
we don't go somewhere know what it
reveals is the take the tail Osen to
being right it's like there's a dynamic
relation that's already there in a sense
as a potential in you know in this anna
gothic thing in it very much
any and its ugliness Leland's book right
now trying not to try but you know
coupon from the from the Taoist
tradition about you know again because
I'm trying to get because this is very I
think relevant to the Socratic project
yes like you said if you try ok this is
our agenda we're all going to encircling
we're gonna see God or something
nothing's gonna happen but of course if
you're just sort of passive right
nothing's gonna happen
like there's it's like you that's what I
mean it's like doing Tai Chi it's like
doing jaws you've got it
you gotta set it up but it has to catch
for itself right yeah yeah yeah yes yes
absolutely
and now here's that um there's a few
different threads but there's one in
which I'm really interested in in this
thing that you said in our email
exchange about Rogers right they brought
us right up to that point right which is
we were tired we're breaking out Rogers
and and all that kind of stuff and at
the end you're like you know and then
there's Socrates which is about
basically transforming and rot Rogers
lose about healing and he's like in the
day I'll pick Socrates right yes yes
yeah that's right that now that's that
third thing right where is where is that
there's this relationship between you
and I and the dialogue right but then
there's this other thing that we're
starting to talk about which is because
I'm realizing like as we've been talking
about this is pretty much all I've been
interested in with was circling right
like right there's a lot of stuff around
relationships because it's that that's
the form that we we take right is
looking at each other but but for me at
the end of the day it isn't about deeper
relationships as as the as the end goal
right it's really about it's really
about what kind of what even kids are
calls forth those relationships and this
this third thing right that happened so
you and I are dialoguing and then
there's this other thing that starts to
show up right I think is
of like that you could say that the
philosophical intimacy of this kind of
I'm think transcendent that that it's
some way realizes itself in here's the
Socratic circle that comes back around
like realizes that it was the ground we
were already standing on very much
that's not just personal disclosure
right but it's in many ways its
transformative disclosure and foreign
disclosure right you're like that's all
I'd meant when I was offering Socrates
beyond Rogers is because right there's a
sense in which there's there's there's
an aspirational quality that emerges I
mean and this again this circles back to
Heidegger because when Heidegger sort of
you you know he he brings out that the
logos is the gathering together so that
it comes to belong together right he's
that part of the meaning of logos had
been for buried behind sort of word
reason study and then he brings back
well no but there's a more primordial
meeting of and so that's what I'm trying
to get out with dia logos that know
we're talking but then there's and
that's what I mean there's something
takes shape and then it it's it is
normatively grounding but also vetting
what belongs in the dialogue right it
right and that's and I and that's why I
think people start using very sort of
spiritual language to talk about that
yeah that emergence and that's clearly
what what but Plato's invoking in the
dialogues in a lot of in a lot of places
and I guess like I said I'm trying to
hold these Jordan often uses this thing
about he's juggling balls so we got we
got I just want to recap because I don't
great you got that we've got the
back-and-forth like right and then we've
got that as people are an agave ik
they're ascending right there so there
there's there's this coordinated mutual
disclosure and that's why it feels like
love because mutually accelerating
disclosure is love right between reality
and the psyche the depths of reality in
the depths of psyche are adducing
calling out to each other and that's
that's the ontological and then theory
see Oriya are dialoguing with each other
and yet and then and i think what you
put your finger on right now is theirs I
would say it's the fourth there's a
fourth thing that between all three of
those that's really hard to speak but
it's but it's taking shape between all
three of those because those three
that's why I was trying to do with the
axes model they're not they're not all
fog '''l to each other they're highly
coordinated yes each other right right
is that that thing is that the horizon
that that brings the four ways of
knowing into deeper complexity what
supplies it I think so
is it I think it intimated that horizon
I think I think it does in the sense
that it's only when okay so this is this
is speculation in the a and the good
sense of the word
right we're trying we're trying right
yeah that's what it that's what it says
that's what the S they used to be in sa
a right to try we're trying here so and
that's one of the things also that I
like about the Socratic dialogues people
try in the treatise nobody's trying they
just give you their final results I said
but but Montaigne brought back the
original meaning so I I think when we
get when we were in that state and it's
both intrapersonal and interpersonal and
neutral level right as we said it's all
of those right I think that like I said
that gives us our best coupling so that
we we are we have I'm trying to
platini's his sense of right the you're
reading Shaw's work on theory here right
that we have the the best state of
receptivity for the disclosure of what
is deepest right that we shouldn't be we
shouldn't be idolatrous about that we
shouldn't say now I have seen the face
of God or something blasphemous like
that because that's - that's - that's -
that's to forget our mortality to use
you know some high daguerreian language
there but that's the that's sort of the
best
icon and I don't mean a picture I mean
an embodied present seeing opening
transforming that's our best icon of the
ultimate that's what I think and so I do
think it acts therefore as a normative
touchstone for us on coordinating the
four kinds of knowing wow that's my
that's my best attempt they think of
Ellis isn't be with the attempts this is
kind of like as as David White would say
may we have a kind of conversation that
our our linguistic loop called ourselves
can't survive that you cannot survive
through hang on a sec are just getting
my power cord you got it there we go
totally see it's it's so just kind of
saying all that right so it's sitting
with that how do we do oh I thought it
was really good I mean I feel that I
mean did the discussion both with Jordan
we should have recorded it but we're
gonna maybe record the next one but on
the other hand there's good reason why
we're waiting but the discussion with
him and the discussion I'm having with
you right well it's more than a
discussion it's do logos the new logos
and then and then the do logos that like
that that you've been talking about you
see this is the other thing and I'm
wondering if this is part of the forth
right is you talk about this more sort
of meta dia logos there's a there's a de
logos happening between the dialogues
right and you talk if you often do your
hands furling thing which I really like
right right right and it's like oh it's
such a fantastic gesture because I'm
sort of like a Harry Potter fashion I
sort of see all these globes there are
all these different dialogues and then
they're all right they're all swirling
together yeah and so yeah I think every
one of these and then also what's
happening between them is helping me
helping me tremendously and it again
it's not just theory because I'm coming
to
the conclusion that that one of the ways
in which the meaning crisis expresses
itself to us is in our deep forgetting
of Socrates our deep deep and all of
this what's happening in the sense that
I talk about in this series of sati this
is to deeply remember we're trying to
deeply remember again right right and it
seems to me to tell me if this is this
if this this fits and what we're saying
is that maybe because it's also in the
background you know I'm reading these
books and all these conversations and
there's this kind of backdrop of like
the religion of their religion and and
I'm getting this sense of this
remembering right of the switching
priorities right of where something
something about this this restoration of
the right place of theory in that in
that part in it in that we stand on the
theory that becomes our ground right
that then if it's good theory right it
allows us to see to move towards the
horizon to hear the horizon better right
and it's weaving but it's but that that
it's this relational component like this
this AG agog a this circle the the
Socratic dialogue is though is the
working of those things out but that's
really really important not to diminish
theory at all like this no no very much
very much its rightful like where where
it's powerful right yes and how yeah and
that it's measure is does it it's like
it's measure of whether or not it's
working is does it allow us to to become
closer to the mystery right this is and
I think I think this is and this is
somebody we haven't talked very much
about but I've mentioned it before I
think this is the deep inside of James I
think this is what pragmatism it was
votes to be pragmatism I think has been
sort of that made very thin in terms of
oh it's a particular theory of truth and
it's particularly a theory about sort of
how you do epistemology I think that
what you just articulated is no no
pragmatism because James is much more I
don't know what I want to say here like
religiously a religious sensibility
right but but what never wanting to lose
never wanting to lose the value in the
role of scientific theory that's why
he's very much an important figure for
me as well and so I see pragmatism not
just as like well you know truth is just
what's utility and what we do is we were
just Alaba loose in our epistemology it
no I think what you just articulated is
like no no the deep deep practice of
getting theory in the right place in
there and in the right set of
responsibilities to the other knowings
that's what pragmatism is on about it's
it's about that the propositional
knowing is not self-sufficient and has
to be put into right relationship with
the others and I think that needs to be
explored much more when people are
invoking pragmatism I it's it's not just
you know now I'm not saying that I'm the
only person saying this there are deep
readers I think ro ro w/e reads James in
this way very very deeply so I'm not
claiming any sort of exclusivity there
are there are I think people reading
James and reading pragmatism this way
very profoundly but that's not by by any
means the sort of most prevalent view of
what pragmatism is or what it means
right right so it's like it's that you
could say that it's it's a and I get to
sense with James too like it's in
James's bet he's he's really I read
James and you kind of like end up
somewhere that you yep it's like
circling very interesting like but he
does seem to be he has deep mystical
very much much but it sounds like it's
something
like we're I think you know America you
know pragmatism is understood more like
okay like it's true enough right in
relationship to our goal yeah well but
if we if we replace goal right with like
like a mystery the phenomenological
mystery if the goal is something like
what is the is the you could say that
the the inexhaustible intelligibility
that they're in intimate relationship
with that and how we know is because
we're because people people get closer
to it and they become they become more
the world becomes more filled with sense
right and I'd go stronger and I'm not
trying to bite you I think the world
gets better and I think that's
ultimately what's driving James
pragmatism isn't just you know pick pick
what's useful or utility there's a sense
in which and it's not that it's just
good enough no it's it's it's that it's
making good but but there isn't any kind
of final yes propositional
representation of that so I I think I
mean that's why that's why I'm Ishida
when he's trying when he's when he's
basically creating the Kyoto school and
he looks for something you in the West
to bring into dialogue and the Kyoto
schools a not a good example of
biological rear illegitimate sits the
dot that dialectical relationship is at
the core of nishitani z-- work and and
and being in the tension of the dialogo
s-- is the core place where you need to
get to to respond to nihilism that's
nice too teeny mr. Cheney's main thing
but nishitani what's he getting from
machine and Ishida says when I'm trying
to trade a dialogue between Buddhism and
Western philosophy of course Heidegger
is playing a big role because their
students are predator but who doesn't
issue to explicitly go to with the
experience of the good he goes to James
he goes into James and that's where he's
going when he's trying to craft a
vocabulary that will put these two into
dialogue so that he could start to
respond
through the emergence of nihilism and
the nishitani picks that up and go
religion and nothingness is that's one
of the top five books I read in my life
and I be notified it a couple of times
I've led it with other people
explicitly because you can see you can
see that do you know the way huh
all these things are coming together in
a really profound way right Wow
God is the sense of the tension between
I'm just present to that just in this
conversation I present to it is the kind
of crescendo but also like what we're
talking about like love with the four
ways of knowing leg and then this sense
this citizens deep mystical pragmatism
right of that theory like one of the
measures that makes a good theory is it
is it we can stand on it to move into
more so taking James very deeply it
becomes a viable listen to the word
viable option for us huh right uh and
this is very much like what Frankfurt
talks about when things the opposite of
things being unthinkable when they're
think about for us and he doesn't mean
inferable or imaginable he means that
that an agent arena relationship is
inhabitable and internalized aboe and
liveable for us yeah so I yeah I I that
you have a you have a phrase that you
use that I think I think epitomizes what
you were just saying which is you you
have this race come to terms yeah which
captures both you know conceptualization
yeah articulation but also confronting
being challenged and transformed right
like really coming into contact with
something hey right yeah
yes and well yeah you're right yeah when
you come to terms the terms you come to
allow you to stand up to have more power
on which to come to terms with yeah
you're not avoiding your not dissimulate
your
diluting your cut like we say we're
coming to terms with something right
we're facing it and we're saying okay
I'm going to now open myself up to the
reality of this and but we're also
saying that I what I'm doing in that
confrontation is I'm not going into it
with horror I'm going into it with the
real expectation of intelligibility
being possible articulation being
possible within that I love that phrase
I love it when you use it and you use it
in a perspicacious manner you will use
it at Kairat ik moment within a
conversation you'll bring it out and
what it does is it gives it gives a
turning that it's often needed in the
conversation and your use of that is
really really really wonderful Wow how
procedural of me yeah actually that one
of the things I want at some point I
want to talk with you about how you came
to the four ways of knowing like because
it's it they're just one of those things
where it's it's funny I've tried to like
try to apart but it does seem like
there's something really you keep you
kid everything I think of implies one of
them great so I mean the best answer to
that is I came and this and this is not
meant to be coy or I came to it in
dialog with my students I came to it
from discussing and working out and you
know and you know there was already this
distinction between the proposition of
the procedural already existed within
philosophy and psychology and then as I
started to work with it one of my
students like in dialogue with him yeah
great cos Horace you know this notion of
the perspectival aspect he brought it
and all right and then you know and then
I was talking with another student I was
doing an independent study project with
her and she was saying I get it but what
about the the participatory and it like
she had a very nascent notion of it but
it sort of it was like somebody brought
them matching the tinder in my mind I
was off right and so then I like and
then I really started diving very deeply
into that and but you know
and this all the stuff with Hado and
then you know and then how was that that
period of time when was that ah so I
guess starting around 2006 seven that's
what I'm starting to do that and that's
that's when I start yeah it's when I
start teaching the Buddhism in Kansai
course and the meaning crisis argument
starts to gel so those things are sort
of Co emergent and they're talking to
each other at the same time the what the
COG site of course that you put you put
up on YouTube a few years back is that
like how many of how many of you so that
the Buddhism and Caucasoid course that's
I think that was from 2000 and 15 or 16
and by that time I had been teaching the
course often twice a year for over ten
years so that course had come to quite
you know a kind of I don't want to say
consistency because that's done static
but it had come to a kind of coherence
rain but then when when that happened
kind of the responses I was getting from
people the series when I originally just
uploaded this series just to put it out
there my students would have it it would
be it was more of a pedagogical tool but
when I when I saw the response beyond
just my students um it sort of made me
think and then one of my students again
after he had done the course with me and
finished another quote he came up and he
said it was Allen Keon who whose name
appears in the credits of every episode
he said you know you've got something
here and but the previous series the way
the you know the production value is so
poor it's actually it's imprisoning what
you have to say is preventing it from
being work and he said you know I'm a
professional my dad's a professional and
he's got friends let's really raise the
production quality
and so I thought about that and I said
okay but I want and I came to as I said
like I want a real I want you to really
understand that this is I'm gonna ask
for bigger commitment because I want to
incorporate the whole argument that I've
never presented because I have different
arguments different parts of the whole
argument in different courses and I want
to put them all together and also with
all of my ongoing recent research
because the best teaching is to share
your most current and insightful
learning with people right and I said
that's what that's when I said don't do
this if you don't want to but that's
what I'm gonna ask you to commit to
we're gonna not only improve the quality
we're gonna increase the scope and the
depth of this and try to get right and
he said I'm in I'm in so that's how it
happened Wow okay got it
I'm just a you know it's it's another
thing I just wanted to kind of ask ask
you about cuz I'm I'm I'm noticing I'm
as I understand your work more and as
I'm reading a lot of the the source
material right that like I can I can
feel I can feel in reading basically
because there is this quality of reading
for me that and I think this has
something to do with actually my reading
disability like where where it's a
little bit more for me it's like it's
like I go on a walk with somebody I
don't come out with necessarily what
what it feels like the what I come back
with is not the facts of the walk but
with a different person I feel like a
different person I'm thinking
differently I'm seeing like the world
discloses itself differently to me and
so there's this anyway where like as I'm
reading part of what I'm part of what
I'm also appreciating is the ride that
you've been on right coming in coming to
terms with what you've been coming to
terms with on your videos and listening
to your lectures right I'm also really
present to this had you've been in kind
of deep dialogue with some I think some
authors like some definitely some
authors and philosophers and but
although I get this sense
like after meeting Chris like with a
like a lot of students like yeah okay
one of the things that chris said was he
said you know he felt I really
appreciated he said he said I feel like
my constitute like I'm constituted by in
some sense all of these deep
relationships and conversations
historically like he's um he's like yeah
yeah I feel like I'm constituted by
those conversations thank you very much
as am i and I mean one of the things you
no doubt seeing is the indebtedness I
have to the people you're reading and
what I wanted to want to articulate now
is the indebtedness to my students for
where I am and what I'm capable of doing
and and you know and many of these
students go on to be much more than
students like Chris and Jen song and
Talia and Leo Ferraro and you know
there's so many of my students who go on
to be so much more and Anderson Todd I
mean I did many of my my students go on
to be people who become constitutive of
what I'm capable of doing in the way you
were just articulating III I am deeply
grateful that's why I try so often to to
share yeah credit because because it
because the reality of the distributed
cognition and the dialectic is more
important than John breaking yeah I I
think I just felt I think I just didn't
really appreciate it what you just
replace where they live in you right
it's really interesting because we need
to notice this like like whenever you
talk about the people that you feel
deeply indebted with right and grateful
for there is a there's a dropping back
and there's like ever and they're just
slowing down and you're just like you
feel in the present
it's very much the movie you and what's
interesting is like I can if I if I if I
hold that in mind when you're on the
precipice of the thing like I can feel
very much this in a certain sense
something like something like the-- or
like the the theory in some way in the
role that we're talking about theory of
like on some level all those
relationships right you stand on and
they allow for more right yeah it's it's
very much a legacy right like sort of
within me kind of thing yeah I feel
those those people that I mentioned as
well as as my partnership with Messara
which is a soui generous as we talked
about on the last dialogue but those are
those I don't want to get too out of
biographical here but those around me in
a way that keeps that creative tension
with the stepping to the precipice right
they give me a groundedness so that I
can go even closer to the edge and so
this is something I was going to mention
there's something I like about Tillich
and how he when he integrated Heidegger
and Christianity together he emphasizes
you know the tonus the tensions the
tensions that need to be maintained
always and so so like I don't want to
use a term like anchor cuz anchor sounds
like you know it's holding you back
that's not what it is it's it's it's
it's it's this counterbalancing it's
like you know you take a good stance in
a martial art and in order to make sure
that you can strike and defend right so
you you you you have to be like I often
warned my students I said you know
you're something if somebody's like this
and they're sort of jumping around
chances are you all right but if you see
them sort of think and take a route
you're a lot of trouble that's the word
I want rootedness
yeah see that's it and they they give me
a rootedness yeah so that like a tree
right it's rooted near the precipice so
that it can bring out its branches over
the precipice to get light that has not
been gotten before right but that's here
to the depth of the rootedness that's
you if you're provided you'll pardon the
very clumsy metaphor that's what that's
what I'm trying to articulate yeah
totally
that's what those people are for me yes
yes and that I just appreciate that back
and forth Ness of yeah yeah and then
drop down and the move in this and that
it just well just seems to disclose your
heart but it also seems to disclose
heart right yeah yeah that sense of just
that like that the uniting of both of
those things very much one of the things
I was wondering too about was and I
wanted to cut I didn't being come back
to this in our you know when I'll we've
had five conversations or something like
what in the first one at the very end of
the first one I just remember feeling
quite struck by this thing that you were
I don't think it was the first time you
had seen it but there was a particular
light in which he was showing itself
which I've been thinking about ever
since which is we were talking about the
fundamentalist like place that you grew
up in right things that you said that
was really striking to me was where you
were talking and I actually didn't quite
understand you at first as you're
talking about then when you reveal it
really kind of struck me in a in a big
way which was like yeah I said I have to
be careful not to go back there because
there was this almond --nt sense of
danger right and where you could be
rejected at any moment by this kind of
like I got a fearful kind of God right
or fearsome God and and then you said
but the thing that it sounded like it
was difficult to not go back to was they
the this
of this your position in in that arena
right was so clear until meaningful that
it that it it there's something about
that clarity of the of the self
narrative in relationship to that was
tricky did not go back to well yeah
because like I say the brain prefers
familiarity over anything else you know
like I said people will seek out
familiar sadness over unfamiliar
happiness and so there's an attractor
there like in the state space idea I
think of it is there's two things that I
have to be careful about one is I don't
want to get drawn back into that yeah
because of its seductive familiarity but
the other is to have a reactive thing
where I just reject anybody who wants to
talk to me about God yeah yeah and and
so it's like there's the two of them are
always sort of like you know like the
like more like my hands are doing
they're they're they're sort of you know
constraints that hold me well almost
like to bring him back Aristotle's idea
of a virtue as being between two kinds
of vices right and and so well you what
you're trying to do is set up you know
sets of constraints so that right the
golden mean isn't an average of the
golden mean is - you know sensitize
yourself to excess and sensitize
yourself to deficit to defect so that
you're constantly steering between them
right in and so in that sense that's how
that that's sort of how it works for me
of constantly between these two things
when I'm trying to
many live out live from live out from my
religious legacy so it's very different
from the way and he did such a beautiful
job it's very different from the way
Chris talks about how he's wrestling
with his religious heritage is very very
different
um but you actually which actually means
because we both wrestle we can come into
dialogue but because we have this
significant difference it's a very
fruitful dialogue because we we sort of
compensate for each some what not not
any kind of complete fashion but we
compensate for each other's deficits and
biases when we bring to the when we come
to the discussion of sacredness and the
sacred I I don't know if I could do such
a good job without without Chris or you
know like I said or Anderson Todd who is
somebody I talk about these things quite
quite deeply he also has a different way
in which he relates to all of this so
that again I'm I am constituted like the
the sets of constraints that are the
virtual engine of John drove a key are
constituted in these relationships to
other people and totally and there's
something about to the thing that we
talked about last time which is just
really striking to me would to is wait I
think you had talked a little bit about
your experience of being where you were
you burn you burn some people out like
because is he sorry
yes right I think you are them but that
you were hard on them right yeah I was
hard on one of my previous partners yeah
and yeah I wasn't malicious but it was
very very draining for people that's um
that's something for which I bear a
sense of in the moral sense of and I
bear guilt and I bear a sense of
responsibility again I think it would be
unfair to me to say that there was any
malicious intent but I was caught up in
something that had a hold of me
and you know this the Nietzschean you
look too long into the abyss and it
starts looked back through you and I
it's not that I couldn't let it go in
though in the sense like you know they
addict can't let go of his crack it's no
no if I felt a sense of a calling on of
allegiance of something more that needed
my devotion the you know Yadin has a
book I just bought it I haven't started
reading it that sense of being called
yeah that sense of being called and you
you you you mention it often when you
talk about harkening so I was harkening
to something but you know regardless of
my I don't what to call my ontological
responsibilities nevertheless other
people weren't harkening it who were
nevertheless bound to me because they
were doing what they needed to be doing
in their lives and I think like you know
a tree that is we would've shouldn't be
sort of you know I don't know pushing
other things that aren't rooted that way
over the precipice that's just not right
right yeah so I think that people who
try to embrace me at that time often
found themselves flung out footless over
uh avoid and say why the hell am I here
I don't want to be here and that's like
and I can you know and it was very hard
for me to understand that at the time
because I experienced that given again
the fundamentalism as rejection but I've
come to see now oh that was what was
going on I was I was drawing people to a
place that which I was not affording
them the proper grounding for the place
that I was drawing them to and that was
really I think very hard on people very
hard on people yeah I mean the one
person I think I did that the most I've
apologized to her and and I have really
tried to make amends in the proper sense
of policies without making amends is
there's nothing right
and so I I've tried very much to make
amends in my action and my relationship
to her because I feel yeah
I feel a tremendous sense of
responsibility for all of that so yeah
that's something that's also a template
in my mind of what not to do with people
and there I think there's a time when I
might have done that again and I made I
made that mistake again and so I'm very
with a particular student although
that's that's that's a much more murkier
situation and I don't want to go into it
for confidentiality reasons but both of
those especially the first that I've
talked to have made me that the first
sort of time in my life made me very
very sensitive to that there's there's
there's there's a responsibility above
and beyond teaching and the
disseminating of information it's very
hard for me to articulate and put in
words but to be very very to to
cultivate the appropriate virtue in the
Aristotelian sense so that right people
are drawn into the zone of proximal
development but not drawn over the
precipice yeah totally
and was this a talk you know what's
interesting cuz if I if I when you talk
about like staring into the abyss right
it's a she I don't get the sense I still
I would imagine you're looking right in
the same place but I don't get the sense
that I don't get from you that you're
staring into an abyss it's remember I
said I'm not stuck anymore right you
know and that's very different so it's
gone from being the abyss to being the
inexhaustible huh and that that's lunch
dad that's what that's that's the thing
that nishitani talks about the whole
point about religion and nothingness is
the West because of its commitment to
you know answer theology of Aristotelian
sort of substance and and you know
giving exclusive realness to actuality
and all that sort of stuff I've talked
about in parts of my series nishitani
says that because the because the
Asiatic especially Buddhism doesn't have
that commitment that Taoism doesn't have
that commitment that that the potential
and the possible are just as if not more
real
the actual like that what you could do
is you you could he says what Nietzsche
can't do and we're back to how I said I
found Nietzsche stock like what made she
couldn't do yes the abyss is looking
back through them but it's still the
abyss but nishitani says is no no you
can go from the the no thickness being
an abyss to the no thickness being the
inexhaustible yes and that shift and
that's not a propositional shift that's
like the shift within Tolstoy where he's
you know where without the story of Ivan
Illich you know Ivan Ellicott always
known he was gonna die but one day you
know wifey falls and hurts himself
Ivan ill ik knew he was going to die
right and that's the proposition is the
same but it means all the difference in
the world it's that kind of fundamental
aspect shift yes right so that the no
thickness of nihilism becomes there no
thickness of Shunyata right that's what
that's what I saw in this attorney but
and because I you know I also saw I see
it in in in Plato I don't see it in
Aristotle yeah I think we love sort of
made a move but I see it I see it in
Plato and in Neoplatonism dot and and
you can you know in hiding her try it's
trying to get out of - he talks about
the know thing and the way thoughts and
stuff like that yeah totally it does it
I want to put a bookmark on the on the
Aristotle thing cuz I'm I've been I've
been cracking open Heidegger's going
back into Aristotle I had done that
before I'm like well that's a hole right
there it sounds like a lot of what a lot
of my understandings a lot of Aristotle
that we think of now is is through a lot
of like it's is through a lot of other
different frames that I think Heidegger
is going back and unconcealed these
moments of these ambiguities again
there's a difference there's no
difference because for Aristotle the
unmoved mover is the ultimate yeah so at
the unmoved mover it this is Platonist
as great critique of Aristotle right and
that's that's a that's finally at the
level right of
of the idose but Plato says no the one
is beyond being the one is beyond
essence
yeah that's political and that's what
Platonists points to as paint in Plato
that's not in Aristotle oh you know what
I think you know what it is it's the
sense I get now I have to go back and
probably read this three or four times
to kind of even track the terms that
they're using he's Greek Greek thing I'm
like I don't I have to learn great
ancient Greek I think it's gonna it'll
be helpful but the UM my sense was that
actually that the unmoved mover was more
like it was more like the sense the
sense of two beyond that both revealed
and concealed in its unfolded mist like
there's this kind of just sense in which
the I got the sense of not negation of
of the beyond but that it it revealed in
it it it what this is word that he used
this kind of way of the sea you really
gotta get it's funny I could really get
where like a lot of Heidegger's
phenomenological sure sure off there is
right out of Aristotle I had no idea cuz
he has the Salah he has the scholastic
training before he meets her all right
yeah so that that's deeply deeply
informing him but this kind of like
falling forth as it's withdrawing Ness
of this of I think it's where Heidegger
starts to get a sense of ecstatic time I
think that's I think that's right
so Platonists argues that you know even
in even in the Eternity of thought
thinking itself which is what which was
what the unmoved mover is you still have
a vestige of the subject object relation
and so you have not got I'll use some
high daguerreian language you've not got
to what ultimately grounds the relation
itself between the subject and the
object alright so China says that's
something that must therefore transcend
right the unmoved mover in a deep
fashion and I I I'm in agreement with
both minuses critique of Aristotle right
interesting
after we ought to read more
more of it I've just given different
since reading if any of you up because
the the sense in which oh it's
interesting when you just said that like
I'm a little couple things I'm really
interested I'm I'm noticing it's so easy
to go within this conversation to go
into talking about like your personal
life right in their appearances and
these ideas are and that's what you see
in the Socratic dialogues right the way
they move between the personal and like
and and and and sort of the abstract
theoretical in this fluid mutually
disclosing fashion yes very much
and that's what I meant what I said I'm
so interested if we could you know bring
philosophy a--
yes and circling together yes right yeah
totally and there's a way there's a way
where I do when I do it it happens
implicitly experience it when I'm
talking with you yeah it's it's like
that's one thing I want to start to get
under is what more of the theory yeah
underpinning this particular piece of
something like as the divine double of
the we well yeah very good I like that
that's good that's good right ingenious
I know that that's a very perspicacious
way of putting it thank you I'm gonna
savor that that's good the divine double
of the week that's very good that's very
good guy that's very good thank you
yeah I really like looking for a term
because there's a like since we've been
talking there's of that yeah right and
like I'm like what but there are there
words for it what is that thing that
kind of comes up and is like set but it
seems to function very similar to like
this way in which you could spend your
whole life getting clearer and clearer
about the talos that is calling you
forth right but if you lived a thousand
years you wouldn't it finalized right
that I just appreciate you saying all of
that the last four episodes of the
series the divine double and staying's
whole book on the divine double and how
you see that especially in Tillich and
Corbin and Jung I'm gonna unpack all of
that and how that relates to I think
agnus collards notion of how in in when
we're aspiring we have to relate to the
future self that although we're causing
it it has a normative authority over us
and I think all of those things just
talk to each other so nicely well that's
what I
sorry that's on self congratulatory I
think I make a good case for that he has
episodes yeah totally I can't wait
well I can't wait for those episodes and
I can't wait for beyond Socrates why oh
well you're helping me I mean you're
such a true friend you're helping me
this this dialogue and Gladys recorded
has helped me so much and that thing you
just did with the divine double of the
we my gosh that's like you know a
diamond dropping into the center of
things I just love that that's that's so
helpful yeah yeah I should get going
oh yes should I like awesome thank you
so much my I couldn't survive yeah thank
you so very much I again the manner of
what we were doing and then when you
just brought into the center of the
dialogue a moment ago about the fluid
movement between theory and theory that
that's that's of that's central to to
try to get clear about the logos really
because if like I said if I could I see
it in you and I don't mean this in any
criticism of the people I'm circling
with alright but what what I want is
what I'm looking for it in order to
understand Socratic dialogue and afford
responding to the meeting crisis is a
deep integration between circling and
philosophy of like we've been
exemplifying here and I think what you
talked about the difference between
transformation and healing yeah I think
one of the things that it just there's a
lot of stuff that comes into into
circling right and this is wooder but
some of the difficulty I have had it in
it spreading is that like a lot of
people are drawn to that which this
isn't a criticism pray
no no I get what you're gonna say Yeah
right but they bring a lot of
therapeutic kind of therapy oriented
healing Grothe kinds of things that is
is is like it ends up it ends up kind of
guiding what is or isn't Wow later and
so like one of the things I really want
to do is it's called open up the get
that sense of just like no this is like
this is it like this is a this is
mirroring about like being confronted
with the fact that you are and that we
are not mystery or and getting closer to
it right but it's a way that you can do
that but there's a way there's a way for
me any ways of doing that over and over
and over and over and over again where
it's like I can do it in multiple
contexts is because it's a taste of
something that you can orient towards
right yes very much further okay but
there's something I think about about
what what's still available in our
technological era right they can't they
can't seems like technique can't can't
you can't optimize relationship there's
something still available right
that happens in relationship that and an
experiential level that can reveal that
that we're still that we're still
available for we're still available to
be reached so I think that there's one
of the reasons why I think my attention
is gone our relationship is I'm an only
cut i'm only kid like people hooking
exhaust me right like relationship stuff
like but but I think why I'm drawn to
that particular space is because that
there's still something alive that
hasn't been reached by our modern age
that they it when people experience it
can it still has transformational power
I agree with that
I agree with that I mailed you some
papers and about some side about
this about how grains get into a kind of
synchrony when
you get deep dialogue going and that and
then and then but also some terrifying
stuff where they've actually physically
linked some rat brains together and what
you get is you get a distributed
cognition that can solve problems that
no individual rat brain can solve so
it's kind of a a proof of concept of the
of the processing power of distributed
cognition and then what what is
terrifying in the high daguerreian sense
is they've done that now with some human
beings where they've directly linked
brains together and got the
communication going so there's there's
stuff looming on the horizon that's both
pregnant with possibility but pregnant
with threat that we definitely need to
bring into this discussion now one of
the things that's like interesting about
this is like with relationship there's a
feedback loop that that I think
regulates can regulate that what like
going evil or good bring us good right
and it's it's our it's our it's our
sense of obligation to the other that
much about like there's something about
that to the constraint of that right
that phenomenological sense of morality
of the other that and and face facing
people that 11 else talks about the face
right and there's an on Twitter yeah
yeah yeah and I and one of my concerns
is that this director and I mean the
genies out of the bottle once this
direct linkage stuff becomes available
we're going to lose the face to face
constraining which often carries a lot
of the moral relationship they've just
been articulating well anyways I say you
some papers you can take a look at them
because I okay my friends take care bye
but